So, let's talk about the most
significant releases in Jana over the
past week, including the big GPT5 story.
That release got a ton of backlash, and
I think it's a really mixed bag. On one
hand, GPD5 sometimes really
underperforms the previous models. I see
that. But on the other hand, the Pro
model is better than anything I've seen
before. This is the best model in the
market right now. In my opinion, and I'm
going to show you why I think that.
We're also going to be looking at some
data which shows the actual usage of Gen
AI today and how it developed over the
last year. We have some competitor
platforms like Gemini and Claude
introducing memories, the favorite
feature of most chatb users, and so many
more quick little stories in this week's
episode of AI news you can use, the show
that rounds up all the generative AI
releases and filters for the ones that
are available today and that actually
matter. Let's begin by talking GPT5
because this is the number one story on
most people's minds. It's the number one
model most people use. And I want to
start by reviewing this data and leading
into a discussion on what to actually do
inside of ChatGpt. Now that we have more
options here and how to turn those on.
So this data comes from similar web and
it paints a clear story. One year ago,
Chach5 roughly 85% of the market share
for Genai. Today 78% and the trend is
clear. They've been slowly but surely
losing some market share to competitors.
Deepseek came in strong, but now it's
becoming less and less significant. And
then Gemini has been growing in
popularity now being at almost 9% of
users with the surprising one of Claude
being just at 1.6%. what in my circles I
would say it's like a 60 2020 between
chat GPT and then Claude and Gemini but
the internet traffic speaks a different
story and I think this change in usage
is what inspired GPT5 and that leads us
into our next story which is the
discussion around the GPT5 release I
don't want to spend too much time on
this I could be talking about this for
half an hour but you probably caught
that the backlash against GPT5 was
drastic and most people were very
disappointed with the new model and I
think the disappointment came from one
place in particular and That is if
you're on the automatic model switcher
and you ask certain questions, then it
automatically picked what level of
thinking it wants to use. And what I've
seen happen in practice is that they
introduce sort of a new tier in the
model that is even below GPD40
previously. So a lot of people just
tried GPD5, they got routed to that
version and they received inferior
results to what chat GPT was giving them
before and they were furious. Rightly
so. And I have to say I try to recreate
that behavior that we saw in the first
few days and I haven't been successful
at that anymore. They ironed that out
over the last week. Now what I found is
that most of the GP5 responses come in
at least at GPT4 level. But
nevertheless, to give some power users
the choice back, you can go to the
settings here and enable show additional
models, which is off by default. And I
do recommend turning this on. Especially
if you follow this channel, you probably
know your way around this model selector
at this point. I talk about it
regularly. and it gives you these extra
choices. So, I think I really have two
important messages. First of all, the
hate that was directed at the weekend of
the GP5 model, I feel like has been
ironed out. I think they made that
decision to save costs because the
popularity of Genai has just been rising
and now they're serving 700 million
monthly active users, many of those on
the free account, and they just wanted
to improve the economics of the company,
which resulted in a worse experience for
most people. That being said, I think at
this point, what I said a week ago in
the release video actually stands. I
think for most users, this is a better
experience now. they don't have to deal
with model switching and that weaker
model to me seems to be history and for
anybody who really wants the personality
of GPT40 which I agree is incredible. It
just feels more like a friend than any
other model out there. You get that
choice now. Okay, but here on this
channel we're about the practical
applications. So, let me switch gears
and actually talk about how you can get
this to do more of what you want. I
think I have two points that really
matter here. The first one is a
realization that some of these thinking
models before they did not use memories.
Okay? And now all the GB5 models do.
People don't realize this. They didn't
just improve the model switching. They
improved also the integration into the
entire ecosystem of their features and
apps. So let me demo this quickly to
you. So if I save a memory here that
just says that I love roller skating and
then I go into a brand new chat and I
open up one of the old thinking models
like 04 mini. What do I love? And it
doesn't know because it doesn't have
memories. But if I open up the new GT5
and go to thinking mini new chat, what
do I love? You love roller skating. This
was not the case before. Most people
didn't realize these. And memories are
arguably the most powerful feature for
most users that do not manage their
context manually with custom
instructions or projects and custom
context files. Things that we teach in
this channel and the community and now
even hold webinars and workshop for
companies that teach how to engineer the
context in a way that empowers people
who don't know how to craft the context
themselves. Chat GPT solution to this
are the memories and they didn't work
with most of these models. I think
that's a really important point that has
been completely missed over the past
week. GPT5 has it on all of them and I
think that's great. And the second
practical point I want to make is GPT5
Pro is insane. I do not say this lightly
for anybody blaming me to be a OpenAI
shell on this channel. Guys, I'm not
affiliated with anybody. I haven't even
been in touch with OpenAI. They didn't
give me early access to the models. They
never sponsored me. I'm just here to
find the best product in the market for
myself and then I want to make honest
recommendations to you. Let me tell you
this five pro model. It just works
better than anything out there for the
general purpose queries especially
business related tasks that I love for
writing and coding. I myself am still
torn between claude and chat GPT with
Gemini being super strong too. But when
in doubt GPT5 Pro, oh my god, enough
talk. Let me actually show you. So this
is an amazing prompt that I kind of
discovered recently. What I do in my
free time, I often watch psychology
related lectures and read books. And
what I love is as that knowledge of mine
kind of builds up, a lot of it
translates into AI prompting. And
sometimes I just come up with prompts
like this. What are the components of
some of my favorite activities, hobbies
that I love so much? And can I find
those components in other areas of life?
Essentially asking of what other things
in life would you love based on what you
already adore. This is just the first
version of the prompt. I'll be crafting
this further. But then I proceeded to
give it some activities that I love and
some of the reasoning behind it that I
see there. And then I ran this through
GPT5 which was a good answer. It told
me, hey, with kite surfing, these are
the components. There's technical
mastery, there's freedom, there's
adrenaline and risk, self-reliance, and
more. With paddle, it's about tactics,
friendly competition, social connection.
Entrepreneurship, it's about growth and
experimentation, problem solving,
multiskll integration, impact creation,
and more. And then it gives me
recommendations of other activities
where I could find this. Like similarly
to kite surfing, I could try backcountry
snowboarding, which is actually my
second favorite sport on earth next to
kite surfing. So great recommendation
there. FPV drone flying, which I do too.
And then rock climbing and sailing are
the ones that I'll keep for the later
years of my life. But I've been very
aware of these, let me tell you, like I
do enjoy rock climbing and sailing is
kind of on my bucket list for things to
kind of explore later in life. And
overall, these other answers also kind
of map. I guess there was one surprising
one which was like volunteering to lead
big initiatives in nonprofits but many
of these other ones like running events
or community groups. I mean we run a
community like these are obvious to me
that I also enjoy these and would be
good at this and then it gives me a
little analysis of everything. So this
is the GPT5 response. Okay. Now if I
switch over to the GPT5 pro response I
think it really illustrates how damn
powerful this thing is because this is
like having multiple PhDs in your
pocket. But again this is the pro model.
This is behind the $200 pay wall. Sam
forgot to mention in the presentation
that this is the model he was really
talking about, not the one that's going
to be available on the free tier. And I
think that discrepancy between the
expectations is what caused the outlash.
I just wanted to show you that the pro
model, it delivers and it does it in a
way that I haven't been able to get this
level of quality out of the other
models. Prompt adherence is also
unbelievably good. It never forgets any
detail of what you tell it. Okay, so to
this answer, I'm going to scroll through
this. You can have a look at it if you
want, but it takes a completely
different approach. It takes an approach
as if this was like a research paper on
your interests with the goal of
identifying the patterns and showing you
what you will love in life. And if I had
to score this, I would say GPT5 is like
a level of insight and depth that is
maybe like a five out of 10, whereas
this is like a eight or a nine. Like it
analyzes all the ingredients independent
of the activity. It gives you ways to
integrate it into your everyday life for
each one of them. And then it doesn't
stop there. It comes up with patterns
that you can reuse in different areas in
your life. So it comes up with this
concept of a kite window. freedom first
scheduling where you predefined a wind
window each week that is a
non-negotiable autonomy block where you
just channel creative energy in a
blocked off window just like I would
with some of the other activities I
love. I thought this was genius. Or this
12 experiments per quarter rule where
you start with a hypothesis, give it a
time box and a single metric and then it
gives you implementations of starting a
ship club ladder where you get together
with some people and you assign points
for ship lessons, toolkits, community
contributions, kind of integrating
everything I knew with what I actually
do. A multi-week implementation plan and
then a lightweight way to finish it all
up. And it even offers to create a
template, which is something I find GBD5
Pro does forever. Now, I could keep on
showing you examples like this to prove
the point. Okay, I just picked one that
I thought just really illustrated it
well. For anybody who's still skeptical,
I have another one here where I
basically told it about all the current
opportunities I'm looking at with the
channel. So, this one really is quite
personal. Let me even showing you this.
It's actually putting myself in a very
vulnerable position cuz I'm considering
some opportunities right now between
speaking education and what we already
do. And I was just blown away by how it
structured the output. It gave me
different points of view. One was
focusing on max profit. Another one was
focusing on the maximum amount of
freedom and so on. And it even created
an opportunity scorecard and it ran
different scenarios for me and save
those in a CSV file. Are you catching
this? Chat GPT literally thought about
various scenarios about how the
different things I'm thinking about
could play out and created multiple
documents to help me decide and to help
me see into the future. And from my
experience in this world, I would just
say that it maps onto this IQ score of
the models. Honestly, I'm not exactly
sure how trustworthy this is, but it has
been going around social media where
GPT5 Pro actually reaches 148 IQ, far
surpassing all the other options. And 5
minutes later, we have the template that
we let it generate. Let's have a look at
what it did here. Oh, that looks very
nice. And actually, yeah, I do want the
CSV. So, I'll just go to Thinking Mini
here. I'll just say yes, CSV for Notion
import. And then this is just going to
run some Python code as all the tools
seamlessly integrate into this. And
let's see if I open up notion here. Say
import and give it the daily activity
logs. There you go. That's a way to
score it everything based on a custom
methodology it came up with. And it did
the same thing for some of the other
scoring methods that invented here for
me. And I personally just find that
really impressive and effective. But you
do need the thinking or the pro mode.
When it comes to default GPD5, it's I
don't know. I would say essentially the
same as the models before. And I get why
many people don't like that with all the
hype that was happening, especially if
sometimes it underperforms. But yeah, my
point being open was hyping up this
whereas most people got this. But
understand that on this channel we're
always talking about maximizing the
opportunity here which hides down here.
So naturally, I'm going to be judging
the best version, not the worst. And I
think that one is incredible and I use
it all the time now. Okay, let's see
what's next. Okay, so in case you missed
it, I recently posted this video showing
you how I built a real mobile app with
AI that we even published on the Google
Play Store without needing to code.
Turning our most popular GPT into a
mobile app was a lot of fun and now
anybody on Android can download and use
it. So if you want to build a real
mobile app, too, you should definitely
check out Bubble, the platform on which
I made the app, Sam the prompt creator
on and the sponsor of today's video. So
for me personally, this was the first
project I ever did on Bubble and I went
into it hyperfocused on creating this
app. Once you get into it, you start
realizing how much is actually possible
with the different tools. It is very
customizable and they do give you a ton
of resources to help you get started.
But from all these resources, by far my
favorite are the templates, preset
projects that you can customize. And
from all the different ways to learn,
this is usually my favorite. I like to
take a starting point that gets me right
in the middle of the process. I see how
that works, edit it, add something,
break something until I feel confident
to actually start from scratch on a new
project. And that's exactly what these
templates let you do. or just take them,
customize them a bit and use them as is.
So, for example, there's this free one
which allows you to build a dashboard
with OpenAI integration. This is the
most popular template and allows you to
turn data into dashboards that you and
your team can use to visualize data. And
obviously, this has been made for you to
customize it to exactly what you need.
Or how about this other one, which is a
multi-purposebased template where you
can do way more. And this one allows you
to build websites in no time that also
transfer to mobile really well. And in
total, there's over 1,500 templates in
Bubble right now. So, if you've got a
project in mind, you almost never need
to start completely from scratch. And if
you've ever done a project like this
before, you'll know that editing is so
much easier than building completely
from scratch. So, if you want to build
real mobile apps without code and get
them onto the most popular app stores,
go ahead and try Bubble today. They're
giving away a free month to all users
right now. So, check out the link in the
description to get started now. All
right, now on to the next piece of AI
news that you can use.
So, now we're going to talk about clawed
memories cuz they finally added the
popular feature in chat GPT to claude.
You can enable it if you go to your
settings. It's enabled by default, but
you can check it if you go into your
settings and this function here, search
and reference chats. Allow cla to search
for relevant details in past chats. And
there's this simple prompt that they
make you run when you log into Claude
for the first time. Hi Claude, what were
some highlights from our recent
conversations? And as you can see, it
pulls up some of my recent conversations
here. I really like how it shows you
exactly what chats it references here.
That's wonderful. And then it summarizes
it back to you. So yeah, these are some
of the recent conversations I had with
Claude here. But it made me really
curious about one particular question
and that is how does this feature
interact with projects because that is
my main use case. So I'm going to just
pull up my work context here where I
have my company mission vision values
and overview of our entire company
ecosystem into markdown files here as
context with a little bit of custom
instructions. And I want to see if this
is going to pick up on this chat that
I'll just start in my general folder,
which is I love rollerblading. I'm just
going to say that straight up. And then
we're going to check inside of the
project if it knows that. So I'm going
to go back into the work context and ask
what do I love? And sure enough, it
looks into the context documents, but
there's no mention of rollerblading. So
as they should, projects are still
self-contained folders. But it still
leaves me with one more question and
that is if I say I love kebab which I
actually do
in Austria that was one of our go-to
dishes after school. So it acknowledges
all the context I gave it and then it
says okay and noted on the kebab
appreciation. Okay, I love it. Love it.
Love it. So what if I now say what do I
love? Does it reference the old chats in
the project? Cuz this I would actually
like to see. And sure enough no mention
of my kebab love. Here
>> they ask you how you are. You just have
to say that you're fine.
>> So just like in chat GPT, this feature
only works outside of projects and you
can always see that here at the top
through the breadcrumbs. This is just a
general chat. Whereas this kebab love is
inside of the AI advantage work context.
And this is the number one way I
recommend people actually work. Build
your context into markdown files which
you attach to a project and then group
conversations by topic. You don't want
all context for all conversations,
especially as you get more proficient
with these tools. But most people won't
be doing that. most people will be just
starting new chats and for those
referencing previous chats is actually
super helpful in giving more relevant
answers as most likely their requests
won't be that precise. Now on the same
note I want to point out that also
Gemini shipped a memories feature into
their platform but that feature seems to
have not rolled out to my account as of
yet. They also just tweeted this 16
hours ago, but yeah, three out of the
four big platforms. The fourth one being
Grock, kind of the new kid on the block.
Very smart, very controversial, bit
behind on many features. Doesn't have
memories yet, but all the other players
have this core feature. And I can't wait
to see how this is going to develop
because I think long-term memory is
actually going to be one of the key
ingredients to making these assistants
not just helpful, but truly
indispensable in this modern world. Next
up, I want to talk about my favorite app
in the entire genai space recently,
which is Cloud Code. I think it's
unbelievably capable and this ability
for it to spawn multiple agents, use
them subsequently or even in parallel,
each one of the agents essentially being
a powerful prompt or persona that you
have is unmatched. Especially when you
start adding MCPS to the specific sub
agents, it's just unbelievably powerful.
And I've been really obsessing over this
stuff. Like I find myself staying up way
too late just trying out new think
experimenting, really obsessing over AI
again. Like I haven't for a while now.
And they've been shipping a lot. So, I
want to give you a quick roundup on what
they released recently because I think
what's absolutely amazing here is that
the community comes up with new and
better ways to use it and within a few
days they ship features that do exactly
that. One of those examples is the core
agents feature that I just talked about
that people used to do it manually
through scripts in our community like
two or three months ago. Now there's a
agents feature for two or three weeks
now. Then there's this other workflow
where people have been using Opus to
actually create the plan for what clot
code is going to do. and then sonnet the
cheaper and faster model to execute that
plan. Now this was cumbersome because
you had to switch model you had to do
the plan then you had to switch model
again execute the plan switch model to
continue planning and so on. You could
also do this through custom files but it
was tricky. Now they have a feature
where it does just that. It plans with
opus every time and it executes with
sonnet. Plus they shipped the upgrade to
the sonnet API where it can now handle
up to 1 million tokens. So that's up
from 200,000 tokens before. And all of
this stuff compounds. Okay, so if you
have multiple agents working in
parallel, before the plan probably came
from Sonnet and they just had 200 tokens
each. Now the plan comes from their
smart orchestrator Opus and they have
five times more context each, meaning
you can run five Sonnet agents
simultaneously with a million tokens of
context each. And then they deliver
their plans to orchestrator, which is
Opus, to analyze everything and create
the next step of the plan. This thing is
becoming a powerhouse. And I'm not quite
ready to show you some of the things
that I've been building and playing
around with. Don't worry, I'll do that
soon enough. Right now, I'm actually
holding a community event later today,
showing the community some of the tricks
that I learned in Claude Code and some
of the things that you can create with
these parallelized agents. But yeah, I
just wanted to start to sneak that into
this new show because my personal
feeling is that this is the next big
phase of AI. I don't think it's going to
be GPT6 that's going to completely
change the game. I think it's these
applications that run multiple agents in
parallel and that actually work and can
actually manage millions of tokens and
you get to lean back and let them work
instead of just AI assisting you as you
work. It's still a long way, but I think
clot code is the closest application
that we've seen so far to actually
delivering that. And while it's focused
on development, people are bastardizing
it already for writing life management
and all other types of use cases. If
you're curious about that, I would
recommend you check out this claude code
page on X. They share different projects
and releases from the community and
Enthropic. They're not affiliated with
Enthropic, which at this point, I also
want to point out that neither am I.
They did sponsor us for the Claude 4
release, but honestly, we would have
covered that anyway. And I've been very
consistent in communicating that Claude
are just my go-to models when it comes
to development ever since Sonet 3.5
really. But you make up your own mind.
I'm just here to share what I find, and
I always want to be transparent about
any type of bias or involvement that I
might have. I'm also just human. But
yeah, this is just the number one app
that I've been using over the past
weeks. Hey, quick note. If you're
enjoying this content, don't forget to
leave a like and subscribe to the
channel. Genai to my surprise is still a
lightly technical and very niche topic
and every single like helps out the
channel. And with that being said, let's
get to the next piece of news that you
can use. And then we have one more story
which is this tiny tiny tiny texttospech
model. It's called kitten text to speech
and what it does turn text into speech.
Nothing revolutionary you might think.
Let's have a little listen.
>> Hey, have you heard about kitten TTS? It
is a realistic open-source texttospech
model with
>> not that impressive, right? Considering
some of the competition and now there's
one reason I'm actually highlighting
this and showing you that this exists
because this thing has been going crazy
on hugging face and the reason for that
is one this thing is fully open source
and two it's around 20 megabytes. Okay,
what would I even compare that to? What
is 20 megabytes comparable to? It's five
MP3 songs. It's four to five
highresolution photos on your phone.
It's a 10-second video. It's nothing,
okay? And it's fully open source, so
anybody can build this into their app,
run this offline, whatever they want to
do. I just thought it was really
impressive that a model that is, I don't
know, okay, not very good to be honest.
But this is the level we reached like 3
4 years ago. The only thing that was
free was the Google Translate robot,
which sounds like this.
>> My name is Eagle. How are you? And
honestly, while this might not be much
better, it's tiny and fully open source
compared to the Google product, which I
believe is only accessible through the
API, right? For this search, I actually
want to switch to O3 because it searches
the web incredibly well. Yep, as I
thought, those are cloud only. So
really, I just love this trend of AI
democratizing a lot of these
technologies and making them available
to anybody to build on. I think people
are widely underestimating how much
power AI is going to give back into the
people's hands through software releases
like this and many others that we cover
over time. Sure, the Frontier models are
always going to be in the hands of the
big labs. And there's going to be
certain things that only those can do.
But as they raise many of the crumbs
become widely available, and that leads
into this week's quick hit segment,
which are all the stories that I thought
were worth covering, but maybe not worth
talking about for a few minutes. So, we
just quickly brush over them. And I'll
start with the first one which relates
to the kitten text to speech story
because we got a first tease of Grock 5
coming out later this year. Interesting.
Can't wait to see that. I mean, just as
a reminder, benchmark wise, Gro 4 is
still crushing it on certain benchmarks.
Just adoption is not there yet. I think
that might change with time because of
moves like this. As they progress, they
made Gro 4 free to all users worldwide
right now. So, if you want, you can just
try it out right now. Make up your own
mind on how you like the current model.
And this is what I'm saying. As these
labs race each other, all of a sudden
the consumer is benefiting in that race.
Another quick hit from this week is
Mjourney releasing HD video. This is
720p HD and it can create this type of
quality out of their video generator
which is actually super good. I think
Mjourney kind of carved out their space
in the video generation space. It's just
got the static quality of the image
generator and now you can do higher
resolution. Up until now it was just
480p. So that's nice. As we're talking
about AI video, V3 is finally fully
accessible through the API. Up until now
there was API endpoints but just for
providers like foul where you got the
whole thing in one and now you can do
things like split out just the dialogue
or just the sound effects. They have a
specific preset for cinematic realism
and it just really opens up all the
options for people who want to create
videos on mass rather than one by one.
And that story also leads into our next
quick hit which is Google releasing
their own version of a learning product
just like Chachip did recently. So, not
a model that just responds to all of
your answers, but one that helps you
understand and asks you questions and
doesn't just give you every single
answer right away. Plus, they opened up
a program where they're investing 1
billion over 3 years for American
education. This applies to some other
countries, too, and you can apply for a
free Gemini account if you're a student
or educator or educational institution.
And I just love to see that because
these days, I really see the discrepancy
between people who are just kind of
oblivious to these tools and people who
are really embracing it. That gap has
been there for a while, but it's
widening with stuff like claw code
happening now. This is what I've been
talking about for years. I don't think
people can just catch up in a week or
two anymore. You need to learn about
prompting, which leads into context
engineering. Then you need to learn the
basics of automations and how different
apps interact with each other so that
you can understand how MCPs work and
connect to the prompting component and
then bring it all together in aic system
where you create multiple agents and
orchestrate them. Essentially, it's a
ladder you got to walk up. And I think
initiatives like this are going to help
with catching some people up. And the
advantages mission always has been and
is to show you how to not get left
behind and to show you how to not just
climb that ladder, but get ahead of
others through some of the newest apps.
So that's what we'll keep doing on this
channel by covering the last few stories
we have this week, which actually is
another Google release. This is Jules.
This is a asynchronous coding agent
different from Cloud Code, Cursor, or
the others. This is supposed to work
simultaneously with you on a cloud
server in the background. So, I haven't
used this yet. I think this is more for
larger repost rather than building your
own little apps, but it's fully out of
beta and available now if you want to
check it out. And then lastly, we have
two quick releases. One from Luma Labs
where they have their own video editing
feature now just like Runway released
last week. It looks very similar in
practice where if you're on a paid plan,
you can do these edits where you replace
the background or add visual effects.
This is a product category that is still
just shaping up. These are the first
iterations of it we're seeing. And then
finally, I want to end on the Matrix
game, which is a opensource version of
Google's Genie free last week, the world
simulator that creates entire worlds and
lets you control them with a computer.
Now, you do need a powerful graphics
card. I did some research. Seems like a
4090 would be enough to run this
locally. This thing is fully open
source. So, if you have a 1490, you can
try running this on your own computer.
But, it's funny to see a big release
like Genie Free last week and then
somebody follows up with a open source
alternative. Love to see that. And
that's it. That's what we got for this
week. A lot of small releases, a lot to
discuss. Honestly, I did not expect this
much to happen in AI during an August.
And if you're still watching this, I
would just like to say a heartfelt thank
you for your time and attention. I hope
you get what you're looking for out of
these videos. My hope is that some of
this content inspires people to go out
there, create, grow, or maybe just
create more space in their life to have
more time for what they really care
about, because I know that's what AI did
for me over the past years. Some of
these apps make me just as curious as a
little child. And there's an infinite
amount of things to learn here, which I
love. And I just wanted to thank you for
making that possible by just hanging out
here and learning together. And with
that being said, I hope you have a
wonderful rest of the week.